i think we need to work more
preventatively because i think we're so
i mean in health care in general but i
think especially in mental health care
it's such a reactionary system you know
you don't really get you're on these
crazy waiting lists for psych supports
and you know it can be too late so
in my case i remember having a
conversation with one of the psych
nurses in the hospital and she goes you
know this is actually good that you were
hospitalized because
now you will be
shortlisted you'll like you'll be if you
need psych supports in the future you'll
be at the top of the list
and i just like
why is this what it has to come to for
that to happen for people to receive the
help they need
in a reasonable amount of time knowledge
is power
[Music]
ladies and gentlemen welcome to the
junkyard love podcast i'm here with
heather hutchinson
um heather i have spent last night and
this morning uh reading your book i
didn't get to the end of it
unfortunately um right now um your your
i think it was like ex chapter 21 24 you
were in psychiatric care uh where i left
off so i have a little bit left but
wow
riveting uh your writing is wonderful
i'm reading on audible too
oh are you yeah so being able to hear
your your emotion and the vocal tonality
and the cadence
and um
oh man it's it's it's really good the
audible is very good too like being able
to really have your emotion and
everything come through in that i really
value that so great great work on the
book so far honestly thank you
yeah so um
would you like to give my listeners
probably don't know what what the heck
i'm talking about so would you like to
kind of give your bio kind of give a a
lowdown of of where you're at how we got
connected here um what you were thinking
um and kind of kind of little bit of
your background
yeah so i'm a singer-songwriter
originally i have three albums out
and my memoir as you were saying just
came out in june
and it basically chronicles my life as a
blind person in canada and latin america
and
there's kind of two parallel themes so
there's that and then there's my
struggles with mental health over the
years which culminated in being
hospitalized for psychiatric care during
the covet 19 pandemic and sort of
you know what that was like
mm-hmm
yeah yeah it was it
seems like quite the journey you know
even just so i i was reading it thinking
it would be
you know pretty much just about the
uh how you had mentioned that you were
um
just the the difficult difficulties that
you had um being hospitalized through
coven 19 but then i realized that you
have this whole long back story you know
and you have this whole long perspective
um it and it was it was interesting
reading
you know just the simple things like the
the dorky jokes that people would throw
at your way or like the the corny
typical things that people would say to
a blind person and
as you were explaining them in the book
as i was listening to you on audible
um it would be like oh man that would be
that would be so dorky to hear i would
you know it seems so obvious but
apparently to other other people it's
not so what was your um
let's go back to when you were young so
so what was it like for you for you
growing up you know because these
symptoms that the depression this these
things kind of started at a young age
even
yeah so it was pretty normal like my
childhood was
the early years were really very normal
and then you probably read in the book
around five
people kind of started treating me
differently that was kind of the first
point that i realized that people
thought i was different
um because you know kids at school i
started you know you get more
self-awareness you start realizing that
adults
are uncomfortable around you as well
and so i just kind of started to
withdraw and then there were some family
issues
that i think
exacerbated everything and i think the
anxiety started first i started having
panic attacks when i was about seven and
then i think the depression kind of came
after that um in my early teens because
you know you're constantly feeling
anxious all the time when you get to a
point where you're just like i don't
want to feel this way anymore
yeah right right i mean i think a lot of
people um
i i think i think many people kind of
experience depression anxiety a little
bit later on i i think um i mean of
course not everybody you know many of us
deal with it from a young age for me
with my
spells of depression it wasn't until
i mean i i had a rougher childhood but i
was able to kind of shelf it in in a way
i feel like i kind of bottled down a lot
of these things and then when i was
older they started to really come up and
yours yours was from a young age so what
was it like like being so young and
having you know anxiety attacks and uh
in dealing with depression at such a
young age because i'm sure that was hard
to voice i'm sure it was difficult for
you to kind of even put into words what
you were feeling let alone you know have
an adult really help you out
yeah because i think when you're so
young and
hopefully it's getting better now but
when i was a kid in the 90s there was
kind of this attitude of like oh she's a
nervous kid you know she'll grow out of
it it's fine we don't really need to do
anything about it
which obviously
you know it just gets it's so much
easier to treat the earlier you catch it
so
but yeah like the the anxiety attacks
and stuff it was really hard to explain
because even when you like if a person
gets a panic attack when they're older
if they haven't had one before
like they can feel like they're dying so
as a kid being like seven years old i
had no idea what was happening so i
didn't really tell anybody because
i didn't really know even what to say
about it it was just super strange these
things that would just happen and i
didn't know why
yeah you're like what i so i guess
everybody just deals with this this
seems like a crazy human experience but
i guess we're just throwing with it
yeah
yeah wow wow that's incredible um so so
what was it like for you um
so
as you as you grew older as you started
to cope with and learn more about your
anxiety and depression so how what was
the process of you kind of learning
about it and then being able to voice it
i think
i was around 14
well when i the year before that
somebody i was close to died by suicide
and
everyone was kind of going you know what
people say
like oh how could she was so selfish
um
you know we can't really talk about it
no don't talk about it in front of the
children sort of thing
and i remember hearing that and trying
to process it
and being like you know what like maybe
that's not such a bad idea
so i started making plans to kill myself
and it was actually
kind of
divine intervention why it didn't happen
then and then i was called to the count
the school counselor's office
and she said somebody was worried i
still don't know who or why
so then i was my mom took me to a
psychologist because she called home
and i guess that's sort of when
i started to realize that i guess it's
not you know
that normal something that everybody
thinks about and
you know is prepared to act on
so it became a little bit easier i guess
to talk about at that point
yeah yeah i mean i imagine it was
difficult nonetheless especially at that
young age i think that mental health is
is being more and more normalized
especially through you know social media
in our younger generation is
a lot of our younger generation um
i'm around i'm 29 so i'm millennial but
i feel like a lot of the gen z is you
know it's almost a normal thing for many
of them to grow up um with some form of
awareness around the depression and
anxiety it seems like it's a little less
hard to talk about although still you
know very much a stumbling around
conversation for for many it's it's a
it's difficult to kind of pinpoint um
but yeah so so the
wow yeah like experiencing that back
then and then so were you surrounded by
people who
there was a couple instances in your
book where um you you had one friend i
think it was one of your friends from
peru had said something that that stood
out to me um
what was the common response around the
people that around your loved ones like
when they learn about this of course
they're worried about you how was the
conversation around that was that
something you had to kind of tiptoe
around was it something you felt that
you could fully speak on or how was that
it was super varied you know that the
friend that you're talking about was
really good and
my aunt one of my aunt she's an er
doctor so obviously she was you know
really comfortable to talk about those
sort of things as well
that was about it
um i didn't really want to worry people
you know people don't know what to say
it's it's uncomfortable it's scary
and then it makes
you as the person having these thoughts
feel
like a bad person like these thoughts
are
you know terrible you shouldn't be
having them and everything because you
get that reaction of like oh my god how
could you be thinking that you know
somebody you know the very first thing
they said was you know you can't do it
that would be the most selfish thing you
could possibly do
which is totally the wrong thing to say
yeah yeah so so i've actually heard
someone um um speak about that before
like i i actually had a co-worker years
ago who was
they were going the selfish route like i
don't think they really had contemplated
very much i'm not sure if they were
really aware of how they were sounding
when they were saying it but i think we
should expand on that a little bit what
what what does that mean to you now that
you've had a little bit of retrospect um
and you hear someone say something like
that like that's a selfish act to want
to take your own life what does that
mean to you now
i think it's a really unfortunate
attitude because i think when we're
struggling so much already you know
we know
we know that you know we don't need to
feel worse than we're already feeling
about ourselves and that's just
you know when you're actually going
through it
it feels like you're doing the right
thing it feels like it's altruistic not
selfish at all it feels like you're
doing the world a favor so then
you know when somebody comes back to you
and says no that's selfish it's like you
know you already feel so crappy about
yourself and that just adds to it
yeah absolutely i mean and it's
you there was one point where you
mentioned um
basically kind of pulling that warm
blanket of it's like a comfort of
you know when it comes to depression
you kind of pull over that that warm
blanket and you kind of sink back into
it you know it's isn't it so interesting
you think that people kind of stop in
their tracks a little bit like wow this
person would rather die
you know than feel what they're feeling
that that to me seems so profound but a
lot of us don't really we don't really
intellectualize it because it is a very
uncomfortable conversation for a lot of
people if they've never really dealt
with it and
even when it comes back to panic attacks
i i know multiple people who their first
panic attack they would they literally
go to the hospital they think they're
actually having a heart attack and the
doctor says well you know sorry it's
this is actually you know anxiety this
is a panic attack here's what's going on
in your body and they're they're like no
no that's
panic attacks can't be that bad and sure
enough they can you know and certainly
the uh this you know suicidal ideation
um you know intrusive thoughts all these
sort of things uh
can
they're certainly
of course when someone describes it it's
like wow that that seems terrible i
can't even imagine but then once you
experience it it's it's this next level
uh um just just just terrible thing so
um
when you
let's see where we are i'm taking a
glance on my notes here as we're going
along um tell me about your so
i don't want to i don't want to spoil
the whole book i definitely want to um
you know leave leave listeners the
chance to read it themselves but i am
curious kind of where i left off um
so you were in psychiatric care during
during cover 19. yes um where where did
you kind of come out
on top of it like how are you doing now
are you feeling are you feeling pretty
solid now did you have um any sort of
revelations while you're in there like
what's been your journey a little more
recently
yeah so one night i don't know what part
you're at um so maybe you haven't gotten
there yet but one night i was in the
hospital
and i couldn't sleep they were playing
around with a lot of different meds and
you know that makes things super weird
for sleep being asleep and waking up and
stuff
and
this person was flown in by air
ambulance from a smaller hospital to
this bigger urban center for treatment
and they were
you know in critical condition they were
dying
and
[Music]
they arrived and right after they called
a code blue which is you know somebody
in cardiac
or respiratory arrest
and
i start i was lying there and i started
thinking about this person's family and
being like my god like their loved ones
are going through one of the scariest
nights they will ever have
and i started thinking how can i feel so
much compassion and empathy for this
person's family
while knowing that the decision i want
to make is gonna devastate my own loved
ones and then i started thinking about
this person
and i'm like
they're fighting to live and i'm
fighting to die
and would they trade their place with me
and i realized that i was being given
this choice and
in that moment i had to decide am i
going to live or am i going to die and
if i'm going to live then i need to do
something positive i need this story to
be
more than you know just another tragedy
more than just another statistic and
unanswered question so it was actually
that night that i decided no i'm gonna
write i'm gonna write this book i'm
gonna tell this story for the people who
can't anymore
wow wow so did that feel like a divine
intervention or anything did that feel
like this yeah incredible moment
yeah it was super
super weird i don't know
i think sometimes we're just in the
right
place at the right time and i think in
in the right place emotionally to
receive that message because you know
if it happened a couple of days earlier
or if i just heard the story from
somebody else like it would have just
kind of been like oh that's sad but
you know whatever but clearly i was just
in a place where i was ready to receive
that message
right yeah and you definitely received
it because again like i said the book is
is fantastic the memoir is fantastic um
so what was what what happened after
that so you had this this profound um
kind of perception change you know
you're you're kind of picturing yourself
you're you're you're flipping spaces
with this person in the other room who
is fighting to live and while you're
fighting to die that's a a great way to
word it too by the way um what so what
what happened after that how were you
able to like take action you know
because a lot of times
i feel if we're in kind of a depressive
state where
we will have these moments of clarity we
will have these moments of you know what
you know maybe you feel the breeze on
your skin
um you know you're you're in a
comfortable spot you're around people
that you love and you kind of have these
moments where the mind's a little
quieter
okay you know this isn't so bad i did
have a rough morning i did have a rough
last night whatever um but i i'm here so
kind of
but a lot of times those moments seem
fleeting it seems like you were really
able to kind of catch this moment though
and really you know kind of ride it out
of the of the pit in a sense so how did
you do that
well it's actually funny because things
actually got worse before they got
better after that yeah
but like in a good way sort of
because i feel like before
i was just really going through the
motions in the hospital like i didn't go
to the hospital to get better i went to
the hospital for absolution because
when i was dead i wanted my family to be
like oh well she went to the hospital
you know she tried
so i was just kind of in there like
fighting my time until they let me go
home this you know them keeping me was
not part of the plan
um
but then this this thing happened
and before that like i just felt so
shell-shocked and then the next day
something actually happened in groups
somebody said something
that affected me so much that it was
just like
every
all the grief i have ever known in my
life just kind of all came together in
that moment and
i was just like absolutely devastated
they ended up sedating me that night
and
that was kind of the beginning you know
like that idea the night before was was
a beginning of sorts but then this
like it was kind of like this cleansing
of just like all the pain and
from you know so many years and i
remember like right before
i was sedated like my very last thought
was you know like this isn't how my life
was supposed to go
so yeah i think that was really the
first day of because i actually started
trying then you know like i actually had
these emotions because i hadn't cried i
hadn't you know done anything i was just
so shell-shocked being in there and then
and then it all just kind of opened up
on that day after having kind of that
revelation
that night
and then i i feel like that day was
really when i started to heal
wow wow yeah so that really kind of like
you had kind of two moments of different
experience like so one the night before
that's kind of like your your precursor
and then the next day it was this you
know poking this bag this well of just
all these emotions and things that
apparently needed needed to come up so
was there a lot of
so that day kind of started a trickle
effect
um were you able to kind of look back at
the way you had been thinking before or
the thought patterns that had been going
on and and revamp them or were you
was your brain still kind of feeding you
these continuous you know mean unhelpful
negative thoughts and you're kind of
combating them differently or what
basically i'm asking heather what was
kind of the internal dialogue for you um
during this moment
yeah i think
definitely it takes practice like you
don't sweat you don't flip a switch and
then everything's great right right so i
think that was really the beginning of
it but it's it's been a long road and
it's
it takes constant practice you know i'm
still not perfect at it so
you know it's just so much repetition of
like cognitive behavioral therapy like
okay
what is actually going on is this you
know is this my perception or is this
reality so you know you walk into a room
and you're going like oh my god
everybody hates me they think i'm so
stupid you know all these things and
then you kind of have to
stop and reframe that okay what's
actually going on here is that realistic
or are people you know generally good
who want to see the good in other people
and want to see people succeed you know
which of these two things
is more accurate but that takes a lot of
practice
yeah absolutely i can imagine well so
what what has been your practices since
then what what has been the do you have
you know daily rituals do you have
different habits now that that you put
in place to make sure you kind of keep
yourself
in a positive mindset so me for example
um i'm i i've just changed my lifestyle
in a lot of different ways you know
there's different foods that i that i
try to avoid there's uh you know i'll
i'll try to fast so i don't have
inflammation at certain times of the day
i do meditation yoga a lot of these
things do you have um in anything that
you've kind of like learned over that
has has seemed to help you lately like
through the pandemic through the through
your healing process that you're still
going through
yeah meditation is a big one i think the
biggest thing that helps me personally
is to everyday remind myself
what my purpose is because i think when
we don't have purpose is really when we
get lost so if i can remember that if i
can do one thing every day that makes me
feel like i have purpose
that i'm doing some good in the world
that i need to be here then that is
more helpful
to me than anything else that i've tried
but it's a combination of things of
course
yeah yeah right no i totally agree i
think that that purpose is it's
something that's almost a bit overlooked
as humans we really do have this desire
for meaning you know we we want our
you know it's not so much uh a
self-importance as it is we want our our
life to uh bring value to the rest of
the world we we wanna um
whatever our talents are whatever are
things that only we can bring to the
world we want to make sure that we're
doing that we want to make sure that
we're providing our loved ones with you
know
the things that only we can provide them
with you know um and that and that's
incredibly fulfilling so
when it comes to your music like so are
you working on music almost every day
now is that is that a way that you're
able to provide meaning um is that
something that you can tap into and you
feel okay i worked on i wrote a song or
i did this for 30 minutes i
practiced this thing i played piano for
an hour and okay cool i did my work of
because
as a musician that is that's a way of
providing meaning to other people you
can really
allow them to feel something internally
feel emotions that they didn't know were
laying dormant in them by hearing the
right lyric within the right key you
know like you can really poke that as a
musician it's this super power as a
musician that you have so do you find
meaning through
your music heather
yeah i'm actually just sort of getting
back into it
before the pandemic i was really
struggling already and i actually
pretty much completely stopped playing
music i remember being on stage a couple
months before the pandemic
and just really just going through the
motions and like playing these songs and
just standing up there and being like
i hate this i'm not enjoying this and
that was the last show i played because
i'm like i'm not being fair to the
people who are coming to see this and
i'm not being fair to myself
so and then the pandemic hit obviously
and you know live music kind of stopped
everything stopped
and
you know things are just i think you
guys were like way ahead of us in
opening up so things are just kind of
starting to open up again so actually
this week a friend of mine who's a
producer drove like 27 hours here and
he's like let's um you know
spend five days or something write some
songs and record some songs so that's
kind of like this year the most serious
music i've been involved in recently and
it actually
feels really good i wasn't sure how it
was gonna be but i'm super happy to yeah
be starting down that road again
wow yeah so so what what's the stuff
that you're writing right now does it
feel different does it feel like a new
evolution from from the stuff from
before the pandemic
yeah i would say so i think
i'm actually kind of trying to draw on
some of the
my lived experience and then kind of the
universal experience of like what we all
went through during the pandemic
yeah wow yeah that's i mean yeah it's i
i think that is that's a great place to
um to like narrow down on though is
is you know what what brings you joy and
and for you to
it's it's it's interesting to hear you
even before the pandemic you could start
to hear that you start to feel like i'm
disconnected from this it doesn't
doesn't feel the same because the way
that you described um your album like
when you when you first put those
headphones on and then in the book you
described it so so greatly you know um
it felt felt very pure to you it seemed
like um
so for you to go from that to kind of
feeling disconnected and and wondering
and you know you almost wonder if
something's poking at your purpose it's
like all right well it's time time to
shift you're going to have to learn
something new or you're going to have to
um go through some sort of metamorphosis
here and then it it's very interesting
to think of the type of music and what
it what you're going to be able to
accomplish on the other side you know
yeah in a few years what you're going to
have written is going to be i bet it's
going to blow the old stuff out of the
water in a sense you know yeah yeah i
hope so because i think that was that
was really it like i was just tired of
i wasn't playing really like what i
wanted to play it was more
you know i'm
i'm doing this to
just because it's what i'm almost like
supposed to be doing if that makes any
sense but it wasn't like fulfilling
anymore so
it was kind of like
okay i need to i need to shake things up
and i actually started working on a
project right before the pandemic that i
was like super excited about and then
it all fell apart obviously because of
the pandemic so i think that was really
hard too and i just like didn't want to
play music because
you know
even even just that like it was just
this reminder of how everything was
falling apart and i think some people
really like a lot of my friends and
colleagues really drew comfort from
music during the pandemic and they would
put on you know like these online shows
and stuff i just couldn't be bothered i
didn't have the energy it was just
trying to make it through the next hour
the next day you know all right right
yeah so so i'm actually a dj heather and
i have oh yeah okay yeah yeah so i've
been a dj for um it's around 10 years
now and so i i was working um dj and
audio engineer so when the pandemic came
around for me as well i'm in the the
live event industry so it all changed my
world as well um
and you know
it it was interesting because you're
playing in in clubs and bars and in
casinos and and you know live events and
people are having fun people are having
drinks we're all like we don't think
about our proximity to one another we
don't think about you know being close
we don't think about singing loud or you
know sneezing coughing whatever like
we're just we're here we're existing
we're listening to music we're dancing
we're having a good time um and it
really kind of changed a lot for me i
did a couple live streams even and uh
i'm glad i did them you know i wanted to
to kind of keep keep in touch and keep
doing a little bit of work but
um they all just felt so weird you know
yeah like what what am i playing to you
know it's what are we gonna disconnect
yeah we're gonna you know
pretend that we're having just as much
fun as we did when it was live you know
it's
kind of this facade so yeah it has been
interesting um i i've played a little
bit since since we've opened up um i
haven't really gone full bore i haven't
haven't really played any um big events
i dj'd a wedding uh back in washington
last weekend but
yeah so i'm actually from washington
originally um just moved out to austin
like um less than like five months ago
so i still have some gigs back home that
i have been flying back for but um yeah
so it has been interesting for for
musicians and in performers
um so so what where do you see so as we
begin to open up um
have you really thought about your your
live performances much yet or is that
still kind of like a little bit far off
maybe after you're done recording this
this project or what are you thinking
for live events i've actually been
thinking about them
more and more which is kind of exciting
i think what i'd like to do and and
we'll see how it all comes together
but i would like to you know take some
of this new material and actually tour
it around a little bit
um
while kind of telling my story and and
incorporating parts of my book kind of
into it too so just trying to give
you know this sort of like rounded
you know
sort of performance that that will
hopefully you know help and educate
people
as well at the same time
yeah i think that would be cool like
this entire this moving experience yeah
that's because because a musician anyway
is up there they're they're the maestro
right like yeah they've we have access
to
if you're the one on stage you kind of
have access to the people's heart
strings in a way you know they're
they're ready to saying hey poke these
right emotions i'm ready to feel them
so wow i think that has the potential to
be very beautiful heather i think that
that would be an awesome idea actually
yeah yeah i hope it
comes together because i i think you
know even i don't know
you know even schools or community
groups or just
whoever would you know maybe benefit
from hearing the message of you know
both mental health but also you know
diversity and inclusion and those sorts
of things
exactly
i mean so
as mental health becomes something um
you know like i mentioned it seems like
you you went through it at a younger age
of course you can't speak for everybody
it just seems like there's a lot more
older people maybe even just in my
group around me of people that i see and
people that i knew
it seems like a lot of us didn't grow up
with with the anxiety
and you did so
do you
where do you see mental health now you
know we're we're coming into 2022.
obviously it's riding off the back of
this
um this cover 19 pandemic which is going
to not only exacerbate people's existing
anxiety has already exacerbated people's
existing anxiety and depression um but i
think it's probably going to be it
probably was the creation of a lot of
the first time people are feeling these
these sorts of quarrels um so so where
do you where do you see the kind of the
state of mental health now like where do
you think we should be going where do
you think we should be looking um how do
you think we should be approaching these
conversations
i think
i think that the thing that's a little
bit concerning is this sort of attitude
i think that some people have that once
the pandemic's over
you know people who started struggling
during the pandemic or people who got
much sicker as i did
we'll just snap out of it as soon as the
pandemic is over and it doesn't work
that way so i think
we're really gonna need more resources
dedicated to mental health than we have
now and i think
i think we need to work more
preventatively because i think we're so
i mean in health care in general but i
think especially in mental health care
it's such a reactionary system you know
you don't really get you're on these
crazy waiting lists for psych supports
and you know it can be too late so
in my case i remember having a
conversation with one of the psych
nurses in the hospital and she goes you
know this is actually good that you were
hospitalized because
now you will be
shortlisted you'll like you'll be if you
need psych supports in the future you'll
be at the top of the list
and i just like
why is this what it has to come to for
that to happen for people to receive the
help they need
in a reasonable amount of time
yeah seriously i mean it's it's not it's
not that surprising to kind of point out
the areas that our health care system is
is kind of busted in some ways it's so
great in so many ways but there is other
areas it seems like we're not keeping up
to the to the task of of improving and
changing and developing um
you know what this next stage of of our
health care system is because i think
when it comes to mental health i mean
the amount of people who are dealing
with depression nowadays is is just
skyrocketing it's it's it's upgrading
every year and it seems like kind of the
only answer we we have is
it feels kind of like doctors are a bit
helpless you know they're they're of
course going to try their best but
they're seeing all these patients every
day um what what they're told is to to
prescribe antidepressants um
and it's just this
i like how you said preventative it
reminds me of um
there was a story i think it was
i can't remember who told it actually
but there's basically this this story um
of someone watching it's kind of an
analogy someone watching basically like
there's kids drowning over here okay and
they're okay we need to get those
there's a kid right here that he's
floating down you can see him floating
down the river we need to jump in and
get him so they jump in and they save
the kid and they pull them to shore and
then they look up and there's oh there's
another kid that's coming down the river
and he's drowning oh wow jump in save
him pull him out get to the shore you
look up and there's more kids they keep
coming down the river and so at some
point
we need to get someone to walk upstream
and wonder what that's going on why are
these kids jumping in the river like we
can keep saving them like we're down
here we've got a net you know we're
going to save all that we can we're
going to get them all to the shore we
want to help them but we need to look at
it holistically we need to take a meta
view of this whole scenario and look
upstream what's going on upstream you
know what what's what's causing this
depression
is is it is it a mindset is it uh
are our habits is it our food is it our
just our culture in general is it a
an incorrect thought process is it
a chemical response to something you
know it's
of course there are many people who are
trying to attack and solve these
problems but um it does seem like it's
it really needs to this whole mental
health needs to be put at the forefront
of what's going on you know as we have
these young people who are growing up um
you know kind of
i i i don't know i i just
i think the
the state of mental health does need to
just like you said it does need to shift
from
um you know just dealing with it right
now here's we'll just throw this at it
throw antidepressants at it whatever in
into a more preventative um so so what
in in that field
if there's anybody listening right now
who um you know maybe they're
experiencing some level of this maybe
it's at the beginning stages maybe
they've been experiencing it for for
many years is there any kind of advice
or gestures that you might say to them
like that you've learned
keeping in mind that that you've been in
this position and you may not be
maybe you're not always in the position
to hear it right you know but uh
yeah go ahead go ahead yeah no totally
um so so what what what do you think
like
people who are going through right now
listeners who are experiencing it maybe
they don't know how to handle it maybe
they don't know who to talk to how to
talk about it um they're going through
some level of anxiety depression right
now is there anything that pops into
mind that that you think would be
valuable advice towards them
yeah i think it's tough because the very
nature of some mental illnesses makes it
so hard to get help because you're
reaching out in your reach and that's
you know what uh problem with the system
too is sometimes you have to reach out
so many times before you actually get
the help you need and
it's really unfortunate because how do
you keep reaching out when you don't
feel that you're worth fighting for
but i would say to those people you are
worth fighting for and you do need to
keep reaching out because eventually you
will get the support you need and i'm
not gonna say you know oh tomorrow's a
better day it gets better
you know it does get better that's true
but it's not what you want to hear when
you're when you're in the middle of it
it's kind of an empty platitude but i
think what i can promise is that
you know one day
you'll stop in a moment and you'll feel
such profound joy
and you'll think to yourself like
thank god i stuck with it because i
would have missed this
yeah that's beautiful yeah you really
don't know you don't know what you don't
know you know in that sense you don't
you don't understand how much
how much joy and beauty and love you may
still be yet to experience yes
you have all this this this future life
ahead of you you know it's
and uh what what what is the i think you
even mentioned in your book the
it's a a long or it's a long fix for a
temporary
um issue or something like that like
when they talk about suicidal ideation
um you know you're feeling this they
want to kind of frame it as here's this
temporary feeling and you're trying to
have a long-term fix yeah a permanent
solution to a temporary problem that's
the way to word it yeah
yeah i i think i think that is good you
know because it's so difficult for us in
these moments to really step outside of
okay this is an emotion this is a
feeling that i'm feeling right now i
don't have to necessarily identify with
this i don't have to say this is the
entirety of my being you know for you
for example you're thinking about um you
know you're you know being burdensome
you're thinking about your your negative
thoughts um you don't you don't want to
fight through it anymore you're you're
just done dealing with it but you're
also at that time you're not
it seems like you probably didn't have
access to these wonderful things that
you've done the joy that you've brought
to you all of your friends and family
the music that you've created the the
places in people's hearts that you've
that you've poked with with your ability
to create something and write music
um you know at those moments we're not
thinking about those things we're not
thinking about our accolades right yeah
we're kind of caught in the loops of our
self-despair you know so
um so during those dark moments now that
you've experienced experienced a good
amount of them um
do you have any any um
how do you
how do you hold on through the dark
moments that that's that's my question
how do you how do you kind of like grip
on and just okay i know this is
happening but i know that something
better is worth like how do you how do
you keep the faith and kind of fight
through the storm in those dark moments
i think
all you can do is the best that you can
and if you know if that means you get
out of bed one day and take a shower and
that's the best you can do
you know that's okay and
you know there will come a time when you
can do more but
you know it it's okay to just
need to get through it whatever that
mean you know you need to you need to do
what you need to do and
you need to know that there is support
out there for you and
that you can reach out
i think what was really beneficial for
me and it's kind of funny because at the
time i was like this is so stupid
but with one of my therapists i made a
safety plan
so basically
it start like it lists it's a piece of
paper a document and it lists the signs
like first signs i'm spiraling
and what to you know first steps i can
take and then if that doesn't work you
know it's the kind of this like
hierarchy of steps that i can take
and i totally didn't think it would be
helpful but on that last day before i
went to the hospital
you know i'm thinking of all these
things and i remember this damn
thing that this safety plan that i wrote
with my therapist like the year before
and the very last step on it was go to
the hospital
and so i i was like no like i can't die
with a broken problem and so i actually
went to the hospital and i never thought
that would be
you know helpful but even if it's not
like with a therapist if it's with a
loved one
you know a friend whoever
i think having
a document like that can actually be
really helpful to pull you out of
those kind of spirals those you know
negative
loops that you can get stuck in
right right no i really like that could
you give me an example of some of the
other steps
on there like if someone would maybe
want to create their own simplified
steps step system that they could write
out just just to have it just to try it
as an experiment
yeah so you know it's going to look a
little bit different for each person but
for
me i think the key
to really not spiraling is to have
enough practice with it to know
the very first step or the very first
signs so you can pull yourself out
because it just gets harder and harder
the further down you go
so like for me if i can catch it early
i can go to the piano i can play music i
can
you know call a friend go for a walk
those sorts of things
if you can catch it
you know early enough
then you can do
you know the things that that bring you
joy and and it kind of brings you back
into yourself if you don't catch it in
time then
you know you may need to take stronger
measures you can call
somebody you trust and say you know i'm
i'm not
doing well i need you to you know tuck
up on me or whatever and then
obviously the very last step is that you
always do have that option of going to
the hospital if you're not safe
yeah yeah i think that's a good example
because the
the spiraling is certainly something
that happens and it starts to pick up
momentum you know the deeper down you go
and then it is you're right it is kind
of hard to
it's it's more difficult to grab those
um the the rungs of the ladder the the
deeper down you get into your in into
your you know mental you know negative
fortitude that we create for ourselves
and again like you had mentioned earlier
it is this strange you know
comfort
you know you get farther down you're
like you have of course i deserve to
feel this way and you start justifying
your own kind of meanness to yourself
you know and you want to sink farther
into the cave for whatever reason and if
you can just
find a way to stop it or you have a list
like you said you you have kind of some
rules that okay well i feel myself
thinking these thoughts i feel my body
bringing in these emotions
instead of spiraling i'm going to go do
this or i'm going to call my friend or
whatever so for me um physical activity
definitely helps me if i notice that i'm
kind of caught in some loops if i'm kind
of being you know mean and negative to
myself i'll go you know go for a run
i'll go grab my skateboard and i'll go
take that around i'll go just do some
crazy like 10 minutes of just real fast
yoga stretching moving around whatever
it is it kind of helps
break those thought patterns and one
more thing that i wanted to kind of
point out too that you mentioned heather
is um
at the beginning when you're kind of
feeling this this nihilism this this
negativity
um
the
when you start trying to think
positively or okay i'm feeling i'm
recognizing that i'm doing that
depressing thing again i'm doing that
anxious thing again and i don't want to
do that so i have to do something else
it does feel very fickle at that point
it feels it feels fake to to be like
because so for so for me when i kind of
pull myself out of it um i was doing i
was i suddenly stumbled into all this
you know motivational like tony robbins
um um
uh
jesus can't even think of anybody else
but all these like motivational people
um or affirmations or positivity and it
felt so dorky at first but i started
doing it and i started saying no i'm
gonna sit here i'm gonna not move for 10
minutes i'm going to sit in this room
even though it feels uncomfortable even
though i feel like a dork whatever i'm
gonna make myself deal with it i'm gonna
make myself listen this because my
thoughts that are looping seem to be
negative they seem to be mean they seem
to be making me feel bad so i'm gonna
listen to someone else's voice for a
minute you know so i'd listen to tony
robbins or jordan peterson or some
somebody doing some positive
affirmations and i would really try to
let my guard down and i would try to
just listen if the if the voice in my
headphones is saying i am love i am one
with the universe maybe that's going to
sound dorky and corny at the time but
i'm going to try to okay what would it
feel like if i if that were true i'm
going to pretend cool let's actually
like get into it let's let's pretend and
let's listen to what this is saying
um and
basically it does kind of help you pull
yourself out of those those ruts which
is so so important um being able to kind
of pull yourself out of those moments
and kind of break that that thought
pattern of negativity i think that is is
so important yeah yeah totally and again
just catching it before
you know while you still can do those
things to break that
yeah yeah exactly and again you're
catching it it's not it's not always
going to feel natural maybe at the
beginning it's going to feel dorky it's
going to feel fake it's going to feel
like you're if to me it felt like i was
faking it what am i doing sitting in my
basement telling myself i love myself i
don't love myself what am i talking like
you know but sure enough it's just
enough to kind of give you a little bit
of of a perspective you know yeah it
gets you gets you out of those thought
patterns and gives you a little bit more
distance from them and realize that
you're not your thoughts you know you're
much more
so um so okay so how has your and of
course it's it's it's ever growing right
you know especially when with mental
health i think it's something i think
it's a lifelong journey of sorts as you
as you navigate and you grow from from
certain things
how would you say
how would you say your perspective has
changed from you know the beginning
even when you were young or even right
before the pandemic like when you're
when your thought patterns were were
very negative and just
not non-optimistic
um versus where we're kind of you're
sitting now how has it changed what's
your preference like now
yeah i mean
i think
we all still go there to some extent i
think you know it it is going to be a
lifelong journey
but i'm able to pull myself out of it so
much easier now i have
so many more tools
and
you know the actual practice of using
them because you can have all these
tools
but until you really commit to
practicing and then using them you know
they're not going to help you that much
so
like i said for me it's just constantly
reminding myself doing something every
day
that makes me feel that i'm contributing
to this world that you know i'm i'm
needed here i'm giving something to
somebody else
um
yeah exactly i mean it's
yeah there's something else i mentioned
rick i think of something that your
friend said to you was uh um feeling
useful you know a lot of times yeah we
of course want to feel useful so if you
so does that kind of check off the boxes
for you if you're
you know if you know you do
one hour a day of this or you know two
hours a day of this you you kind of do
your thing that makes you feel useful it
helps it contributes because i'm sure
when you were you know writing the book
every chapter that you got that you got
on page or every chapter that you
recorded was probably
okay you know and maybe i'm still
feeling good maybe this is my healing as
i'm going through it but i felt i can
put it away i can set that to the side
of my desk i did my work for today
that's going to make me feel useful it's
going to help other people because truly
i mean the more people that read this
i'm sure it helps helps everybody in
some sort of way anybody who reads it
um so
the
yeah yeah the the is isn't that so
interesting feeling useful
is something that that we're missing out
on you know so many people in our
society do we just
we don't feel useful you know yeah yeah
and then you get into that whole you
know
the world wouldn't miss me kind of you
know i'm i'm not contributing i'm not
helping anybody i'm i'm hurting people
more than i'm helping them so i'm gonna
you know
not do that anymore
yeah so yeah finding that purpose
finding that being useful
yeah
yeah i mean
that silly thought of you know in in in
in suicidal thoughts when you really
think that your family would be better
off without you and you you will
convince ourselves of that you know and
and it's just
i mean to anybody who has thought that
or they they are thinking that they do
think that i just implore you like have
you have you ever thought that about any
of your friends or loved ones because
probably not that's a really good point
yeah no
never if they said that to you what
would you say you know you'd be like
what are you talking about man i love
you like i'm glad you're here i'm glad
you're my friend you know what
but in those moments we convince
ourselves of that you know
yeah that's a really good point
yeah it's it's a
it's we can be so unreasonable so i mean
i i think reiterating a lot of what we
said is just getting yourself out of
those loops when you're not feeling
useful um if you can try to find
something that only you can bring to the
bring to the world um or or
just something that you particularly do
well you know being useful it's um you
know a lot of times
into the wording of
acts of service a lot of times people
are fulfilled by stepping out of their
own mind um by doing acts of service for
other people so that gives them
usefulness that gives them meaning and
this could even come down to you know
instead of closing off and being you
know
having your hood on when you're in
public maybe try to stand with your
chest out and open doors and say hello
to more people you know maybe you're
making someone else's day by just saying
hi to them by just being polite to them
and that can help you kind of step out
of your own neuroses sometimes too i
think
um
so
let's see where we are here so we've got
i i wish i had finished your book i'm
excited to get to to get back to the end
of it
the
the the climactic you know the
kind of kind of where you came out on
top so
um
as far as your as far as your everyday
thought thought patterns now um are you
are you doing pretty solid like are you
able to stay fairly positive have you
felt um that you're able to kind of hold
on to that that divine moment um when
you're in psychiatric care of kind of
revamping um and kind of going through
that grieving process going through
okay i do actually want to live
where where are you at with all of that
that lately you're still
pretty positive
yeah so it hasn't been a linear process
by any means there have been slip ups
and moments and things like that but
i would say like especially right now
like it it just passed the one-year
anniversary of being hospitalized like
the the first day that i went in
and i was
on the beach
in like one year later on the beach in a
hammock
and i was just like thinking to myself
because i think
you know when when we have these
anniversaries these markers of time
that's because we're seeing ourselves
every day so we might not notice you
know the positive changes we're making
all the time so i'm like laying there in
this hammock
and thinking
one year ago today i was lying in a bed
and psych emergency just like totally
shell-shocked and
and now i'm here you know with the
people that i love and
and my like my god i'm doing so much
better so it was it was a really cool
kind of experience to have that like one
year anniversary and and really be able
to compare
yeah no that that is that's wonderful
that that's very beautiful because in
that moment of course you would have
never imagined that in one year from now
i'm gonna be in a hammock with my loved
ones just with a smile on my face no
exactly you know one year before i'm
thinking in a couple days i'm gonna be
dead so
no he you never imagined that
yeah yeah you truly don't know what you
don't know you know we can't predict the
future so i think really holding on to
that hope and that faith um of
hey i'm going through something right
now i'm i'm definitely going through i'm
not going to deny it i'm going to try to
face it as head-on as i can try to have
courage and look at these things that
i'm going through um but i'm also going
to remember that it's not forever i
think i think remembering in in
holding on to maybe i don't know exactly
how the future looks maybe it's going to
be a little while before i'm you know
in where i think i want to be but i'm
gonna hold faith to it and i'm gonna
know that i'm gonna i'm gonna weather
this storm i'm gonna i'm gonna hold on
through this this mental health thing
one more thing that i did want to
mention um i've been trying to find ways
ways to word it because i heard someone
else mention it and it really kind of
sticks out i think it's a good way to
help um to help us all kind of wrap our
heads around mental health stuff is um
you know
we don't choose it for one
there's there's certainly no reason why
anybody ever
like in it's the same way as you know if
someone um
someone like you know rips the meniscus
in their knee or or they have like an
injury um or or they they break their
arm it's like they didn't choose to do
that you know it's um you sure it
happened through some sort of
in these cases physical but it's it's
basically something that happens in our
body that we're kind of having to ride
out you know it's it's it's a response
in a lot of ways to um a lot of the
internal dialogue and so it's basically
you know just as you just said someone
with a broken leg you you look at them
you're like oh of course they didn't
choose to break their leg they would
prefer it not be broken it's kind of the
same way when it comes to mental health
and reminding ourselves of that of hey i
don't have to beat myself up i don't
have to go the extra mile and say that i
suck for for having these thoughts you
know i don't have to add on a layer of
like oh i'm i'm
because a lot of times we start having
these thoughts and we start labeling
ourselves being more mean to ourselves
for even having them and so just kind of
accepting this is something that humans
go through
and
when you can heal from it or when you
can
begin to heal from it or even
hold it you know sit with it experience
it rather than
you know suffer just simply suffer from
it it gives you a little bit of
perspective and i think i think our age
our generation too heather is um
we're going to have a lot to teach the
younger generation because like like i
mentioned i think you know with all this
technology all this social media um
our comparison to one another and you
know just all this stuff that keeps
adding up that we've all experienced but
it does pile on i think that the younger
younger kids are going to be you know
looking for some advice and some people
to
to share their experience of how how
they went through the similar things and
how they came out on the other side so
yeah what what you're doing in the story
that you're sharing heather is is very
important um i i commend you for i think
it's i think it's wonderful um the the
book is
i mean i i recommend audible i i read a
lot more through through audible because
i do too yeah yeah i i like to be able
to move my body and kind of distract
myself or use my adhd to my advantage
while i
there you go get a bunch of stuff done
yeah yeah yeah some sort of multitasking
but um yeah so
it's a great book i i
invite anybody to check it out
we are getting up here in time so if
there's anything else that you wanted to
mention but i did want to make sure we
get
your
your website out here so where can
people find you can they find more
interviews of you where can they get
your book give us the lowdown on all
this heather
yeah so basically you can find
everything on my website which is
www.heather.hutchison.com
h-u-t-c-h-i-s-o-n everybody always adds
in like the extra n then yeah um
and then the book is
there's links on my website to the book
but as you said you can find it on
audible
amazon
um apple books google play books
pretty much everywhere you buy your
books and
it's available in print and
uh ebook and audiobook and i also have
facebook instagram twitter
which is all on my website as well
yes yes
wonderful cool well i mean everybody
definitely go go add heather go check
out her book i think you will thoroughly
enjoy it
i of course recommend the audiobook
because you can hear her vocal tonality
and oh my gosh heather when you were
when you were talking about um um what
was it bibi
yeah oh man yeah like because i can hear
that you know a little bit of the
quivering in your voice and i was just
shedding a little you know i'm missing
my my dog didn't pass away but he's back
home when i moved away um so it just it
really strikes on the heartstrings um
and it's a very very relatable um very
relatable reading so
you know you did a great job heather um
yeah and
so
yeah everybody definitely go check out
all of heather's stuff heather thank you
so much for not only spending your time
but for also just having the bravery and
the courage to voice all of these things
that you've been through you know you
you have you have an interesting and
beautiful perspective um i think i think
that life has
has been very interesting for you you
know it's really led you through things
but i think that you've been able to
keep uh a powerful and very helpful
perspective so the fact that you're
willing to
you know stand on stage with a mic in
your hand and talk about it or or you
know
stand in in your office with uh with a
pen in your hand and write it you know
whatever it is sharing your story uh is
is powerful it's helpful and it's it's
valuable thank you thank you so much for
having me
of course of course well we'll be in
touch i'll send you some emails and keep
you posted when this has come out
you have a good rest your day heather
and listeners you have a good rest of
your day as well remember you're not
your thoughts and if you haven't drank
any water today if you haven't stretched
if you haven't done some physical
activity
get out there and do it drink some water
stretch love yourself practice self love
everybody have a good rest of your day
take care heather you too better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
uh
knowledge is power
[Music]
you